{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "While living in East Aurora, this president appointed Nathan Hall as his clerk, and he would go on to serve as this man’s Postmaster General. While serving on the Ways and Means Committee, this man helped author the Black Tariff. This President finished third in the Election of 1856 while running under the Know-Nothing Party. The Fugitive Slave Act of 1850 was passed under the presidency of, for ten points, what successor to Zachary Taylor?",
      "answer": "Millard Fillmore"
    },
    {
      "question": "During this war, the Treaty of Ilbersheim stripped Maximilian Emanuel of his lands after he was defeated, along with the Duc de Tallard, near Hochstadt. Great Britain gained a monopoly on the Atlantic slave trade when the asiento was transferred at the end of this war, in which the Battle of Blenheim [BLEN-em] was fought. This war was sparked by the death of Charles II and ended by the Treaty of Utrecht. For ten points, name this war in which Philip V extended Bourbon rule to a certain Iberian country.",
      "answer": "War of the Spanish Succession"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was the result of the “Biennio Rosso,” or “two red years.” A king refused to authorize Luigi Facta’s use of force to stop this event, which led to the following year’s Acerbo [ah-chair-boh] Law granting one party a parliamentary majority. Michele [mee-KAY-leh] Bianchi and Cesare [CHAY-sar-ay] Vecchi organized this event, which prompted Victor Emmanuel III to transfer power to the leader of the Blackshirts. For ten points, name this event in which Benito Mussolini seized power after his men entered the capital city of Italy.",
      "answer": [
        "March on Rome",
        "additional information, like Mussolini’s Blackshirts marching on Rome"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Leibniz’s version of this invention made use of ten “teeth.” Wilhelm Schickard’s drawings of these devices predate Blaise Pascal’s commonly cited “invention” of them. Early modern examples of these devices utilized Reverse Polish notation. Hewlett Packard released one of these devices in 1972 that allowed for operations equivalent to what could be done by slide rules. For ten points, name these devices, produced by companies like Texas Instruments, which allow you to perform mathematical computations.",
      "answer": "mechanical calculators"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man rose to prominence as a subordinate of John Jervis at the Battle of Cape St. Vincent. This man’s forces intercepted Pierre-Charles Villeneuve after they left Cadiz. This man, who lost an arm while leading an attack on Copenhagen, ordered that the message “England expects that every man will do his duty” be sent aboard his flagship, the HMS Victory. For ten points, name this British admiral who won the Battle of Trafalgar.",
      "answer": "Horatio Nelson"
    },
    {
      "question": "This non-Europe continent’s “Character” was described in an 1830 work by Hegel that elucidated the idea of the “Absolute” in philosophy. Jean-Paul Sartre wrote the preface to one work by an author from this country that applied Marxist principles to colonialism; that work was Frantz Fanon’s The Wretched of the Earth. Edward Said [sai-eed] argued against the stereotyping of the northern part of this non-Asia continent in his Orientalism. For ten points, name this continent that was divided up by Europe during its namesake “Scramble” in the late-19th century.",
      "answer": "Africa"
    },
    {
      "question": "Sailors aboard this ship launched an expedition to Corn Hill, which was then looted, according to Nathaniel Philbrick. On one voyage, this ship was forced to abandon the leaking Speedwell. Passengers aboard this ship included the captain Christopher Jones, military advisor Myles Standish, and future governor William Bradford. For ten points, name this ship that landed at Plymouth Rock, carrying the first pilgrims to the New World in 1620.",
      "answer": "Mayflower"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer included a piece in memory of Emperor Maximillian in the third of his Years of Pilgrimage suites. He wrote a piece that depicted a Cossack hetman being tied to a galloping horse, Mazeppa. This composer’s “Bagatelle without tonality” was meant to be his fourth Mephisto Waltz, and he wrote twelve particularly difficult Transcendental Etudes. For ten points, name this Romantic piano virtuoso who composed nineteen Hungarian Rhapsodies and inspired a namesake “mania.”",
      "answer": "Franz Liszt or Liszt Ferenc"
    },
    {
      "question": "Frederick Douglass once said that it was easier to do this activity well “than to repair broken men.” A book about this activity downplays the importance of rigid schedules and, in its seventh edition, advocated a vegetarian diet aimed at combating obesity. That book on this activity was the best-selling book in twentieth-century America after the Bible and famously begins “Trust yourself. You know more than you think you do.” For ten points, name this activity for which a proper method was outlined by Benjamin Spock, a pediatrician.",
      "answer": [
        "raising children",
        "parenting",
        "“build strong children”, the exact Douglass quote",
        "equivalents that relate to raising babies and/or toddlers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This country passed the Objectives Resolution as the basis for its constitution. It fought a nationalist movement in its eastern half with Operation Searchlight and its incursion across the Line of Control started the Kargil War. The Lahore Resolution proposed the creation of this country, which lies on the northwest side of the Radcliffe Line. For ten points, name this South Asian nation that, in 1967, officially moved its capital from Rawalpindi to Islamabad.",
      "answer": "Islamic Republic of Pakistan"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The US Marines incorporated this game into an ad with the caption “Get off the firing line [...] that’s a safety violation!” Norwegian Prime Minister Erna Solberg was photographed playing this game during a Parliament session. In a 2016 speech, Hillary Clinton attempted to capitalize on this game’s popularity with a Get Out the Vote pun. Nintendo’s stock value surged by 120 percent in the week following the release of, for ten points, what Niantic mobile game in which users may find a Pikachu while taking a walk?",
        "answer": "Pok´emon Go"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Shortly after the release of Pok´emon Go, it was discovered that a Pok´eStop and gym were accessible at the Panmunjom Joint Security Area in this region along the 38th parallel. Niantic promptly removedthem,becauseit’sprobablybadpublicitytohaveyourcustomersshotbyROK[spellit]patrolling soldiers here.",
        "answer": "Korean Demilitarized Zone or Korean DMZ"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man disfigured his left eyebrow after jumping out a window when his wife caught him in a room with a nurse. A helicopter operator supposedly heard “two loud booms” during the jet crash that took this man’s life. A training facility named after him is found in Star City. In April 1961, this man exclaimed “Poyekhali” after successfully leaving Site No. 1 at Baikonur during the Vostok 1 mission. For ten points, name this Russian cosmonaut who was the first human in space.",
        "answer": "Yuri Alekseyevich Gagarin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another landmark Russian space traveler was this passenger on Sputnik 2, the first animal to orbit Earth.",
        "answer": "Laika"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The head of this animal faces the viewer to symbolize the present in Titian’s Allegory of Prudence. A bust of a Roman emperor wears the skin of this animal and shows him holding two golden apples and a club. This animal is frequently shown with Saint Jerome, who legendarily tamed one, and a winged version of this animal is used to symbolize the Evangelist Saint Mark. For ten points, name this animal, a Nemean one of which was killed by Hercules.",
        "answer": [
          "lions",
          "Nemean lion after “bust” is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This emperor was portrayed as Hercules wearing the pelt of the Nemean lion in that aforementioned bust, in which his facial features and hair resemble his father.",
        "answer": "Commodus or Lucius Aelius Aurelius Commodus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The failure of this bill inspired a manifesto, addressed “To the Supporters of the Government,” denouncingapresident’s“dictatorialusurpation”ofastate.Anexceptionforpositions“merelyministerial” and “military offices below the grade of colonel” was made in this bill’s 14th section, which stripped citizenship from certain Confederate officers. An ironclad oath was required by, for ten points, what proposed Reconstruction bill, far stricter than a preferred ten-percent plan, that Abraham Lincoln pocket vetoed in 1864?",
        "answer": "Wade-Davis Bill of 1864"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Co-sponsor Benjamin Wade was a senator from this state, which was also the home state of John Sherman and William McKinley.",
        "answer": "Ohio"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A failed hunt for this creature with an ox-head is depicted on the Altuna Runestone and the eighth Ardre stone. A god takes nine steps after slaying this creature; in another story, that god lifts the foot of this creature after it is turned into a colossus cat at Utgard. This creature is cut off of Thor’s fishing line by the giant Hymir, and the releasing of its tail will start Ragnarok. For ten points, name this sibling of Hel and Fenrir, a giant snake in Norse mythology that encircles the world.",
        "answer": [
          "Jormungandr",
          "the Midgard Serpent",
          "the World Serpent"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Midgard Serpent is closely related with this ancient symbol that depicts a serpent eating its own tail. The first known appearance of this symbol was found in the tomb of King Tutankhamun.",
        "answer": "ouroboros"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This leader was captured, and hundreds of his subjects killed, in the Massacre in the Great Temple. Bernal Diaz del Castillo’s Historia describes this man, speaking from a balcony, being stoned by his subjects while telling them to retreat from their enemy. Cuitlahuac [kweet-lah-wok] succeeded this man, whose death caused Pedro de Alvarado and hundreds of Europeans to flee the city in La Noche Triste. For ten points, name this ruler of Tenochtitlan whose reign ended with the invasion of Hern´an Cort´es’ conquistadors.",
        "answer": [
          "Moctezuma II or Montezuma II",
          "Moctezuma Xocoyo"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Aztec rulers weren’t given numbers; Moctezuma “the second” was a Spanish invention, and he was known to the Aztecs as Moctezuma Xocoyo [sho-koy-oh], with Xocoyo meaning “the younger” in this Mesoamerican language. This language is spoken by over a million people in Mexico today.",
        "answer": "Nahuatl language"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Elisabeth Achelis proposed one of these things to the United Nations, where it was vetoed by the United States. Charles-Gilbert Romme created one of these for the French Republic in 1792, although it was abolished by the Catholic Church in the Concordat of 1801; that one of these things was used for 18 days during the Paris Commune. Because one of these things wasn’t accepted in Russia until 1918, the February Revolution actually began in March. For ten points, name these temporal systems, including a Julian one that was reformed by Pope Gregory XIII.",
        "answer": "calendars"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As part of a push for standardization of units and measures during the French Revolution, the French Republican Calendar had this many days in a week and this many hours in a day.",
        "answer": "10"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the aftermath of this event, Ken Salazar claimed it was his job to “keep the boot on the neck” of its perpetrator. The aftermath of this event involved extensive use of Corexit disperseants, which CEO Tony Hayward controversially claimed were used in quantities negligible in comparison to the “very big ocean.” This event, which took place at the Macondo Prospect, killed 11 people and destroyed a facility leased to BP. For ten points, name this 2010 event, an explosion and ensuing oil spill in the Gulf of Mexico.",
        "answer": [
          "Deepwater Horizon oil spill disaster",
          "Macondo blowout, oil spill, disaster, etc. before Macondo is said"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Ken Salazar’s quote came in his role as this Cabinet secretary.",
        "answer": "Secretary of the Interior"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "America in the Pacific Theater",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "General who stated “I shall return” while fleeing from the Philippines.",
          "answer": "Douglas MacArthur"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battleship that became the site of Japan’s surrender.",
          "answer": "USS Missouri"
        },
        {
          "question": "1942 American victory that included the sinking of the Akagi and Soryu.",
          "answer": "Battle of Midway"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle off the coast of Australia where the Lexington was lost.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Coral Sea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lieutenant colonel whose namesake raid was the first to bomb the Japanese home islands.",
          "answer": [
            "James Doolittle",
            "Doolittle Raid"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Commander-in-chief of the Pacific Fleet for almost the entire war. He names the second-most-recent generation of carriers.",
          "answer": "Charles Henry Nimitz"
        },
        {
          "question": "Solomon island whose invasion let the Americans complete Henderson airfield, which was partially built.",
          "answer": "Guadalcanal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commander-in-chief of the Pacific fleet during the attack on Pearl Harbor; he was removed from command shortly after.",
          "answer": "Husband Kimmel"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Hanseatic League",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire in which many cities of the League were located. Much of its territory became modern Germany.",
          "answer": "Holy Roman Empire or HRE"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sea on which the Hanseatic League conducted most of its trade. It is bounded by Scandinavia to the north and Russia to the east.",
          "answer": "Baltic Sea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city that hosted a League trading post at the Steelyard until Elizabeth I ended their license.",
          "answer": "London"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northern power that fought the Hansa for trading rights under Valdemar IV.",
          "answer": "Denmark"
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city of the League, located on the river Trave. It was near members like Hamburg and Kiel.",
          "answer": "Lu¨beck"
        },
        {
          "question": "Member of the League, now a modern capital city, that was founded by the bishop Albert and defended by the Livonian Order.",
          "answer": "Riga"
        },
        {
          "question": "Band of pirates based in Visby that harrassed Hansa shipping.",
          "answer": "Victual Brothers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Name given to Hansa trading posts. Large ones include the Steelyard and the Peterhof.",
          "answer": "kontor"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Mongol Conquest",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Grandson of Genghis Khan who finished the Mongol conquest of China and established the Yuan Dynasty.",
          "answer": "Kublai Khan"
        },
        {
          "question": "City sacked by the Mongols in 1258. It was the center of Islamic learning and culture.",
          "answer": "Baghdad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trade route on which the namesake good flowed from China to the West that flourished under Mongol rule.",
          "answer": "Silk Road"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colorful splinter state of the Mongol Empire, founded by Batu Khan, that dominated Russia in the fourteenth century.",
          "answer": "Golden Horde"
        },
        {
          "question": "Principal heir of Genghis Khan who built a fixed palace at his capital of Karakorum.",
          "answer": "O¨gedei Khan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Law code instituted by Genghis Khan to maintain order in the Empire. It was overseen by Chagatai.",
          "answer": "Yassa"
        },
        {
          "question": "General who was undefeated in the service of Genghis Khan and led the Mongol invasion of Europe.",
          "answer": "Subutai"
        },
        {
          "question": "Empire that ruled Central Asia and Iran until the Mongol invasion of 1218. Genghis invaded after Shah Ala ad-Din Muhammad executed Mongol envoys.",
          "answer": "Khwarezmia or the Khwarazmid Empire"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Artist Stephen Fan has documented the recent formation of one of these institutions among casino workers in Montville, Connecticut. Part of Philadelphia’s example of this was demolished for a convention center, and the one in Manhattan has grown to take over almost all of what used to be (20 pts)",
        "Little Italy. Ceremonial arches known as paifangs often are found at the borders of these neighborhoods, the oldest of which in America can be found along Grant Street in (10 pts)",
        "San Francisco. For ten points, give the term for these immigrant enclaves where one might find people who speak Mandarin."
      ],
      "answer": "Chinatowns"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One member of this family married the Marquess of Hartington while her father served as U.S. Ambassador to the U.K., then died in a 1948 plane crash. Another member of this family owned a farm in Maryland called Timberlawn, where a day camp evolved into the (20 pts)",
        "Special Olympics, founded in honor of another member of this family who had undergone a lobotomy in 1941. Patricia and Rosemary were among the daughters of Rose, the matriarch of this family, which names (10 pts)",
        "Harvard’s school of government. For ten points, name this prominent Massachusetts political family whose other members include Robert, Ted, and John."
      ],
      "answer": "Kennedy family"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this nation, the Legionnaires’ Rebellion was led by Horia Sima. This Legionary State lost territory in the Second Vienna Award and was ruled by several conduc˘ators. This nation, which originated as a union between (20 pts)",
        "Wallachia and Moldavia, was the base of a secret police called the Securitate [sec-ur-ih-TAH-tay]. Ion Antonescu supplied Nazi Germany with oil as he ruled this nation, another ruler of which was (10 pts)",
        "executed on Christmas 1989. For ten points, name this Eastern European country once ruled by Nicolae Ceau¸sescu [cho-chess-koo] from Bucharest."
      ],
      "answer": "Romania"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A ship of this name had its cannon, the Peacemaker, designed by then-captain Robert Stockton. A city of this name was briefly the site of the U.S. capital at Nassau Hall. Hugh Mercer died leading American forces at a battle of this name, where a (20 pts)",
        "garrison under Charles Mawhood retreated after George Washington’s assault. An explosion on board a ship of this name killed (10 pts)",
        "Abel Upshur but left sitting president John Tyler uninjured. For ten points, name this site of an American Revolutionary War victory that followed the Battle of Trenton, a New Jersey city home to a historic university."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Princeton",
        "Battle of Princeton",
        "USS Princeton"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler placed Chlotar IV on the throne of Austrasia after winning the Battle of Vincy. This leader came to power after defeating the Neustrians under King Chilperic II and Ragenfrid at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Ambl`eve [AM-blev]. In this leader’s most famous victory, enemy forces believed their loot was being raided and thus retreated; that victory occurred when he came to the aid of Odo, Duke of Aquitaine, against (10 pts)",
        "Abd al-Rahman near Poitiers [pwah-tee-ay]. For ten points, name this Frankish Mayor of the Palace, victor at the Battle of Tours, and grandfather of Charlemagne."
      ],
      "answer": "Charles Martel or Charles the Hammer"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During the 2012 election campaign, this politician said that the opposing party’s policies on regulation would “put y’all back in chains.” In 2008, Christine O’Donnell ran against this man for his Senate seat, which he resigned nine days into his (20 pts)",
        "seventh term. This man’s son served as state Attorney General and planned to run for governor until he (10 pts)",
        "died of brain cancer in May 2015. On January 12th, 2017, this man received a Presidential Medal of Freedom with Distinction from his boss. For ten points, name this father of Beau, a former Delaware Senator and Vice President of the United States under Barack Obama."
      ],
      "answer": "Joe Biden"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These people performed a ritual killing of the missionary Carl Volkner, sparking the East Cape War. After Henry Menzies was appointed to collect a dog tax from these people, they were led into rebellion by Hone (20 pts)",
        "Toia. These people made the design of their pa forts more effective after a series of civil wars was triggered by the British introduction of (10 pts)",
        "muskets. William Hobson believed he had been appointed governor after these people signed the ambiguously-worded Treaty of Waitangi. For ten points, name these indigenous people of New Zealand."
      ],
      "answer": "Maori people"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In one work, Nathan’s lover tells the Brooklyn novelist Stingo about this location and how she attempted to seduce its commander. In one work, a train heads to this location as Madame Sch¨achter [SHEK-tair] is beaten for claiming she sees fire. (20 pts)",
        "Primo Levi’s novel If This Is A Man describes his experience at this place. William Styron’s novel Sophie’s Choice focuses on Sophie’s decision to have her daughter Eva (10 pts)",
        "sent to the gas chambers at this location. Elie Wiesel’s Night is primarily set at, for ten points, what largest Nazi concentration camp, located in Poland?"
      ],
      "answer": "Auschwitz-Birkenau"
    }
  ]
}